<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Mahesh's Blog</title><link>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on Mahesh's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 May 2023 11:36:39 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Postgres setup for local development using Docker</title><link>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/dev-postgres-setup-using-docker/</link><pubDate>Sat, 13 May 2023 11:36:39 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/dev-postgres-setup-using-docker/</guid><description>When doing back-end development or just fiddling with SQL, installing postgres the traditional way may not be very convenient for many reasons. This post describes how to run postgres for local development using docker and docker compose.
One important advantage for me is getting the latest version of postgres, since I tend to use a stable linux distribution.
There&amp;rsquo;s already some amount of documentation for postgresql official docker image. But few things are less than obvious if you&amp;rsquo;re a beginner like me.</description></item><item><title>Non-algorithm optimization of K closest elements Java solution</title><link>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/lc_optimize_k_closest_elements/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2023 07:07:17 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/lc_optimize_k_closest_elements/</guid><description>I am a weird creature in my friend circle for using Java to do DSA problems. (Everyone else uses C++). I am not that good anyway in Leetcode, so at least I will learn some more Java by doing this.
Here&amp;rsquo;s the puzzle I was attempting to solve: Given a sorted array and an integer x, find k elements closest to x in the array (Leetcode #658).
The solution is very straightforward: find the lower bound or upper bound of the element in the array using built-in binary search, then expand the range using 2 indexes.</description></item><item><title>Leetcode #995: Minimum number of K bit flips</title><link>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/lc_995/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2023 11:03:56 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/lc_995/</guid><description>This is my solution and logic for Problem 995 on Leetcode. This is actually copy of solution I posted on discussion forums.
I find it a little hard to get the initial intuition &amp;amp; optimization from O(nk) to O(n), and as usual, other solution posts are very terse. So I thought it is worth to explain a little more.
Problem statement You are given a binary array nums and an integer k.</description></item><item><title>OpenMP and rand() function - A small story</title><link>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/omp_rand_critical_section/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2023 18:35:13 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/omp_rand_critical_section/</guid><description>I have a parallel programming subject this semester, and as usual, there&amp;rsquo;s also a lab in which we try and execute small programs. Mostly OpenMP programs.
First program is to find the value of Pi using Monte carlo methods. We have to then measure the performance with different number of threads, and tabulate it.
Usually, when we add threads using pragma omp parallel for directive, we expect the program to take less time.</description></item><item><title>About Me</title><link>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/about/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 07:54:01 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/about/</guid><description>Hi, I am Mahesh.
I am a soon-to-graduate CSE student, originally from North Kanara and currently studying in Bangalore.
Broadly, my interests in computer science revolve around systems, languages and tools.
You can contact me through email, net [dot] mahesh29 [at] gmail [dot] com, or through twitter handle @never_inline.
Projects jnigen - An experimental JNI bindings generator for Dart and Flutter. It&amp;rsquo;s a GSoC 2022 Project.
rrip - Bulk image downloader for Reddit.</description></item></channel></rss>