<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Linux on Loop Invariant</title><link>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/tags/linux/</link><description>Recent content in Linux on Loop Invariant</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 15:38:10 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/tags/linux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Some tricks for Bash shell interactive usage</title><link>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/bash_interactive/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 15:38:10 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/bash_interactive/</guid><description>&lt;p>While I am not a strict command line affectionado, I have found myself to spend significant time in the terminal, especially when doing devops-y work. Here are some things I learned which will improve the speed when working in terminal.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Note that many of the snippets here were found by me / edited long back. I may not be able to attribute the correct source of each snippet. Let me know if you know the original sources of any snippets posted herein.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Exploring distroless docker images</title><link>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/distroless/</link><pubDate>Sun, 27 Aug 2023 20:53:10 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/distroless/</guid><description>&lt;p>I recently discovered the concept of &lt;a href="https://github.com/GoogleContainerTools/distroless">distroless&lt;/a> docker images. However, this project is quite a few years old.&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The name may be quite misleading (much like &amp;ldquo;serverless&amp;rdquo;) - as distroless images are actually based on Debian (currently Debian 11, Bullseye). However, they don&amp;rsquo;t contain most of the stuff which is there in standard debian image, which such as all the command line executables (&lt;code>coreutils&lt;/code> etc..)&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="whats-there-in-a-standard-debian-image">What&amp;rsquo;s there in a standard Debian image?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s pull and inspect a standard debian docker image:&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>