<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Mahesh's Blog</title><link>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Mahesh's Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2023 15:31:43 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Ephemeral MySQL for local testing using Docker Compose</title><link>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/mysql_local_using_compose/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Oct 2023 15:31:43 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/mysql_local_using_compose/</guid><description>Why? Many times tests are run against a simple database like H2 or SQLite, whereas production uses a heavier DB like MySQL. However, its many times desirable to run testing with the real DB. For example, when the application makes use of DB-specific features or quirks, it&amp;rsquo;s required for proper testing.
Once upon a time it took long time to setup MySQL through distribution package manager, and tests ideally need ephemeral environments.</description></item><item><title>Exploring distroless docker images</title><link>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/distroless/</link><pubDate>Sun, 27 Aug 2023 20:53:10 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/distroless/</guid><description>I recently discovered the concept of distroless docker images. However, this project is quite a few years old.1
The name may be quite misleading (much like &amp;ldquo;serverless&amp;rdquo;) - as distroless images are actually based on Debian (currently Debian 11, Bullseye). However, they don&amp;rsquo;t contain most of the stuff which is there in standard debian image, which such as all the command line executables (coreutils etc..)
What&amp;rsquo;s there in a standard Debian image?</description></item><item><title>Usefulness of Go templates in command line tools</title><link>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/go_templates_in_command_line_tools/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Aug 2023 08:10:08 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/go_templates_in_command_line_tools/</guid><description>Almost every time I see awk in a shell script, it is to extract a particular column - like awk '{print $1}'.
Much has been written and said about how the plain text output of command line tools isn&amp;rsquo;t very flexible. Therefore powershell uses an object paradigm, where nobody understands what is going on. It appears a few tools, like Azure CLI have just defaulted to printing JSON. But this also breaks some long-developed intuitions like using grep or other UNIX tools.</description></item><item><title>Building jnigen - A Java bindings generator for Dart</title><link>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/building_jnigen/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2023 19:11:21 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/building_jnigen/</guid><description>Caine: Then why bother?
John: Maybe I am wrong.
John Wick 4, (2023)
It&amp;rsquo;s been a long overdue to write a post about my past year&amp;rsquo;s Google Summer of Code (GSoC) project. jnigen is an experimental bindings generator which aims to provide Java interoperability for Dart. It works by generating wrappers which call JNI through Dart&amp;rsquo;s FFI (Foreign Function Interface).
I developed the initial versions of this package under the guidance of Daco Harkes and Liam Appelbe from Dart team.</description></item><item><title>Running PostgreSQL locally for back-end development using Docker</title><link>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/postgres_local_using_docker/</link><pubDate>Sat, 13 May 2023 11:36:39 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/postgres_local_using_docker/</guid><description>When doing back-end development or just fiddling with SQL, installing postgres the traditional way may not be very convenient for many reasons. This post describes how to run postgres for local development using docker and docker compose.
One important advantage for me is getting the latest version of postgres, since I tend to use a stable linux distribution.
There&amp;rsquo;s already some amount of documentation for postgresql official docker image. But few things are less than obvious if you&amp;rsquo;re a beginner like me.</description></item><item><title>Non-algorithm optimization of K closest elements Java solution</title><link>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/leetcode_optimize_k_closest_elements/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2023 07:07:17 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/leetcode_optimize_k_closest_elements/</guid><description>I am a weird creature in my friend circle for using Java to do DSA problems. (Everyone else uses C++). I am not that good anyway in Leetcode, so at least I will learn some more Java by doing this.
Here&amp;rsquo;s the puzzle I was attempting to solve: Given a sorted array and an integer x, find k elements closest to x in the array (Leetcode #658).
The solution is very straightforward: find the lower bound or upper bound of the element in the array using built-in binary search, then expand the range using 2 indexes.</description></item><item><title>Leetcode #995: Minimum number of K bit flips</title><link>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/leetcode_995/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2023 11:03:56 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/leetcode_995/</guid><description>This is my solution and logic for Problem 995 on Leetcode. This is actually copy of solution I posted on discussion forums.
I find it a little hard to get the initial intuition &amp;amp; optimization from O(nk) to O(n), and as usual, other solution posts are very terse. So I thought it is worth to explain a little more.
Problem statement You are given a binary array nums and an integer k.</description></item><item><title>OpenMP and rand() function - A small story</title><link>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/omp_rand_critical_section/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2023 18:35:13 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://mahesh-hegde.github.io/posts/omp_rand_critical_section/</guid><description>I have a parallel programming subject this semester, and as usual, there&amp;rsquo;s also a lab in which we try and execute small programs (mostly using OpenMP).
First program is to find the value of Pi using Monte carlo methods. We have to then measure the performance with different number of threads, and tabulate it.
Usually, when we add threads using pragma omp parallel for directive, we expect the program to take less time.</description></item></channel></rss>